howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts so to Jim
rut show calm that's Jim rut show calm
today's guest as Sara kins fodder Yerkes
high chair I'm glad to be here yeah Sara
and I go way back
you know she went to work for my office
of the CTO at what's now Thompson
Reuters right out of college as I recall
is that right that is correct
21 years old oh my god kids today kids
that we had a position we called the
assistant to the assistant it was
essentially a slot we reserved for high
potential people fresh out of college
basically they worked as a troll for my
administrative assistant did all what
anything needed to be doing and the plan
was to quickly promote them and
something in our line department if they
showed themselves to be worthy and Sarah
definitely did was quickly promoted into
our recruiting and HR organization or
she did all kinds of good things she
then left I guess after I left some time
and joined web methods a very
fast-moving DC area tech startup where
she helped drive their talent
acquisition strategy then she went on to
a career or bringing her expertise in HR
organizational design leadership culture
strategy etc to many companies through a
consulting career and I loved I picked
this up on her I think LinkedIn bio and
she's a co-founder or something called
the badass Women's Network which I can
say is definitely not a lie even though
I know nothing about it so if somebody
out there and listener land wants to get
a holier for consulting services in
these many areas how do I get in touch
with you probably the best way is
through my my LinkedIn profile or just
Sarah at blue sky be Lu sky strategy
comm and we also have a website out
there all right that's good she'll do
your good work
so to our first topic one of those we
wanted to dig into a little bit is
what's today's multi-generational
workforce like how does it differ from
the way it was back say 21 years ago
yeah that's a good one although I did
want to add one thing do you remember
when you left Thompson and you went to
Network Solutions I did a brief stint
with you there you had set me in to go
find out what was going on with the HR
department and they quickly put a bounty
on my head do you remember that I do I
thought you worked there and I looked on
your LinkedIn it wasn't there so I said
maybe I hallucinate it which is
certainly possible
I do remember giving you a lecture on
how to live on $10,000 a year and I
thought it was there no that was
actually when I was trying to get the
job at Thompson you tried to convince me
that I didn't need to live in Arlington
that I could find a cheaper place in
Herndon that I could live off of beans
and lentils have all the nutrition I
needed I mean it was it may have been a
little it might have been $10,000 a year
whatever it was it was ridiculous but
you know I mean the network solution
thing ended quickly because the web
methods guys came to meet with you and
you introduced me to them because they
were looking for you know they were they
were growing quickly right and so they
were looking for help and you're like
hey go check these guys out and I was a
little nervous at the time because I'd
worked with you for a good bit at that
point and obviously you know it'd only
been a couple of months I mean maybe
weeks since I'd left Thomson and been at
network solutions but I did end up
leaving obviously with your blessing
you're like yeah go do it I mean this is
gonna be a cool thing but it was a crazy
brief stint at network solutions done
the last yeah I think you didn't get
along with the HR Queen as I recall no
she sucked yeah that was it was not the
kind of really cool HR organization that
we built at Thompson that was for sure
now we agree eventually cleaned it up
and got it better but it was never as
good as the one we created from scratch
that's for sure well and I think it also
had a lot to do I mean you know the
people that you had both at Thompson
vice you know the people who were
I mean you know you had a person that
was much more the traditional HR right
but there were a lot of lot of different
things askance in that culture as well
so not just HR bunch of difference for
day I'm sure that was a turnaround from
almost top to bottom well we had two
good departments we had a really good
finance operation and a good legal
operation pretty much everything else
was definitely in a very serious rebuild
restructure in some cases even restart
but we did it yep yep anyway let's hop
into our into our topic the
multi-generational workforce today and
compare it to when you enter the
workforce well I think the thing that I
find most interesting about the
workforce today is first of all we're
dealing in some industries right we're
dealing with the potential to have five
different generations in one
organization and I think that just
presents a whole lot of different
challenges I'm not necessarily bad some
good but challenges nonetheless
particularly for managers as they're
trying to figure out you know how do I
manage these people with different
generational approaches to work and
different needs so I think that that's
pretty interesting that we we haven't
seen that and yet here we are you know
everything from pre baby boomer to you
know the current generation Z is that
really any different than back in the
day and we had all those generations I
don't think we had them at Thompson
Reuters technology operation but you
know most businesses in those days had
people from 18 to 65 yeah but I think
that the difference between so if I
think about you being the oldest and me
being the youngest no I'm totally
kidding you weren't all this but you
know that traditionalist what I you know
what's called the traditionalist so pre
baby boomer and then Gen X right I was
the Gen X that was kind of when
everybody was like oh my god these you
know this Gen X group they're crazy
they're you know asking for too much
engaged in too much but then now we've
got you know other generations that have
come since then and they have a
completely different take on you know
work how they want to work you know
everything from simple things like when
are they gonna show up you know a we've
got a nine-to-five environment yeah
screw you I'm not gonna do that so I
think that just the differences in the
generations is now so much more present
but I think back then we really had
probably three right that we could think
of in our office yeah I guess that's
right today we have boomers there's
still some of them hanging around for
sure there's Xers and then there's
Millennials and then the beginnings of
whatever you're gonna call the post
Millennials
I think it's gen Z so for so we went
from three to sorta four though I'm not
will see how different the newbies are
with the Millennials I sort of see them
as a continuation but that that may not
be right we'll see mm-hmm how do you see
the Millennials and then gen Z differing
from compare and contrast them with the
Gen Xers and the baby boomers in all
honesty I think it really in large part
has to do with the influence of you know
technology in their lives
I mean Generation Z I mean there are
true digital natives they've they've not
known anything different you know so and
that and it encompasses their life and
not necessarily in a bad way it's just I
mean that's that's who they are and so
they see the world very differently then
you know the what's left of the baby
boomers and and even them you know the
Millennials at some level but I also
think that that really influences their
appetite for it's not necessarily
traditional work it's just traditional
ways of working I know that here in
Charleston something that I found that's
really interesting is that we've got an
influx especially an influx in in
technology so the state's trying to make
it really beneficial for companies you
know to come to South Carolina through
tax incentives and and whatnot but
really the people are coming here in
droves because they want this quality of
life and there's a lot of people you
know out of college in their 20s that
want to be here because they want easy
access to the beach and they
want the year-round climate and you know
they work from home for companies all
over the place
and I I think that they just decide you
know for themselves what's the life
gonna be that I want to live and then
I'll figure out how to get to the work
or the work will actually find me
because their talent is in high demand
so I would have never done that I mean I
was all about you know how am I gonna
get to a you know get to work at a great
company and be around you know really
smart people and in a position where I
can learn and I can you know I can grow
and I can come and I can work my way up
and I don't think that's their mindset
does that make sense I've seen it with
some of course I've seen it with
Millennials and Xers too I mean I know
Xers who you know especially as they've
gotten say a bit older said screw the
corporate rat race I'm gonna go live in
Portland Oregon and I'm gonna get gigs
on the internet so it's not like this
that's an entirely new thing it may be
that the percentage of people of the
newest generation maybe a larger
percentage of them doing it you know and
then I think it's that that's their
mindset out of the chute right like I
mean I'm definitely a part of that you
know Gen X who said yeah I'm not gonna
do that right I mean that's in large
part where I went to consulting because
I kind of foolishly thought the
consulting would be something that I
could you know would give me more
freedom and that's not the case but I
think especially Generation Z is that
way out of the gate their personal lives
and their careers are not different it's
kind of one in the same and so they're
driving you know their life and and the
ways that they want to work and where
they want to live in all of that you
know on on their own and I've I don't
know that I've ever known you know kind
of more a gutsy er I think generation
from that perspective it kind of reminds
me of the Boomers when we were young you
know hell I hitchhiked around the
country for two years screwed around did
this and that slept under bridges didn't
really give too much of a fuck about
career for a couple years and you know
and quit jobs to go do startups based on
the the sketchiest imaginable
fundraising and so I think there fair
number of us boomers were like that too
you know fact I've often said that I see
a lot of similarities between boomer
Millennials and maybe even more with the
new gen Z's or whatever they're gonna be
called you know let's set on having to
follow our nose through a career so I
see that it's a good thing and you know
not that different than the kind of yeah
at least the hippie-ish aspect of the
Boomers I can see that and I think I
think there's a lot about especially
Generation Z that's still undefined but
I think that to your point you know
they're very community oriented people
you know I think we see that play out
obviously a lot on social media which
they're very comfortable with and I
think there's a good in the bad aspect
to that but nonetheless I mean they're
very in the very community-oriented I
think that they're very I think they're
they're realistic at you know similar I
think to to boomers but again I mean I
think there's there's parts of that
generation that are still evolving and
undefined that's for sure and I also
suspect that the kinds of digital nomads
you're talking about are very heavily
concentrated in the cognitive elite you
know people who do things like computer
programming or video editing or you know
podcasting I suspect like in every
demographic group the vast preponderance
of people have you know fairly normal
jobs you know work at Walmart or you
know work in a you know in an Amazon
warehouse or what-have-you so I think we
should be a little careful to make sure
that this conversation is most likely
about the college-educated cognitive
elite and probably working in kind of
heavily tech influenced careers
absolutely yeah and I had you know again
I mean it's a lot of you know what I
surround myself here in Charleston with
right is is some of the technology
startups and technology companies in
general that are and there's not you
know this isn't like there's not a ton
of them but there's a good and growing
number and you know the struggle I think
for any company quite frankly but
certainly in in technology with talent
and being able to find talent in fact
some of the interesting things I think
you know since I left the DC area that
I've been able to do is really help DC
based companies that need talent you
know especially technical talent access
that down here you know it's not
expensive and quite frankly in many ways
it's better quality because I mean you
can get all kinds of quality but that
it's saturated you know and now that
Amazon is opening up a big footprint up
in the DC area I mean it's gonna become
more so but but yes for sure I agree
it's it's really the the tech sector
that were or the the tech community that
that we're speaking to yeah the DC area
was kind of an interesting place to
build tech companies what I remember of
it was it was dominated by the Beltway
bandits and the and the Beltway bandits
had a strength and a weakness one they
had a zillion jobs but the weakness was
because the way they had to pay people
based on government contracting scales a
player's got paid the same as C players
so if you remember our strategy was to
essentially strip-mine the Beltway
bandits and steal all their a players
and and some of their better B players
and leave them with the C players but I
still remember Bob Hall who was kind of
our rabbi at Thompson corporate
headquarters he was on like the Business
Roundtable or something and he's gotten
a call from one of the big-time CEOs at
one of the Beltway bandits saying hey
Bob your Thompson Technology Group down
there in DC is you know they're being
very very aggressive in their recruiting
they're grabbing a whole bunch of our
best people you know please tell them to
stop there's any way Bob immediately got
on the phone and called me up and said
hey Jim I don't know what the hell
you're doing but I got this call from
blah blah blah blah who I won't mention
and whatever you're doing keep doing it
and so we did yeah I mean and I'm sure
you know nah I mean we had a little but
I had a little bit of experience out in
California in my web methods days
because we had an office out there and
had made a couple of acquisitions out
there but I mean the technology
environment in DC yeah I mean it's you
know everybody's getting into that game
right and so and you've got you do
you've got your Beltway bandits which is
different than other you know the the
San Francisco's the New York's and the
Boston's they don't have that massive
federal government influence
it's a bear for them to be able to pay
for the type of talent that they want
which leaves it you know makes it
interesting for technology companies to
be able to go in and grab people but you
know is a very aggressive environment
nonetheless to recruit in I mean we had
to pull out all the stops yeah and again
you have to use tricks as we did right
we differentiated ourselves I still
remember one of the problems with the
Beltway bandits is they make everybody
take drug tests so we decided screw that
if you want to smoke reefer go right
ahead in fact I fought a big battle with
that clown who was the head of HR at
Thomson at the time who was that weasel
I remember the name now anyway he wanted
to force us to it to do drug tests and I
wrote a letter to the CEO of Thompson
making the argument saying I'll get my
shitter people smoked reefer blah blah
blah and I will I'll give him credit he
sided with us and said if that's one of
your competitive recruiting advantages
then go for it so we did yeah you
remember you know back in the day - I
mean we you know when Thompson's
strategy was really you know shifting
right to become more technology focused
in fact it's crazy to think about you
know that particular point in my career
I mean obviously I was very young but
that point in time I mean I was a big
inflection point for Thompson right to
really go from you know more of that
traditional brick and mortar to just
using technology and new ways to deliver
data to deliver information but remember
we had a big college recruiting effort
all over the country and you know the
the Harvey muds and the mi t--'s and all
kinds of awesome schools with great
computer science programs and you know
that was a benefit even in those
environments because a lot of the places
that there was those kids were looking
to go to work we're still you know kind
of have the stiff upper lip right and we
we didn't have that where we were trying
to not have that you know that brand
yeah we had to communicate the brand -
right as you know I famously said fuck
at least once in every time I was
interviewing somebody for a potential
job because I didn't want them to get a
false perception of what our place was
like right you know we're the kind of
place where the CEO says fuck if he
feels like it yeah
whenever I think about recruiting for
instance when I write ads I used to
write a lot of recruiting ads and I
wrote them to both attract and repel I
want to attract the people we want but
frankly I wanted to repel kind of rigid
people who weren't gonna fit into our
culture I suspect all that today would
get me an HR jail but oh well it worked
back in the day yeah you created a very
narrow funnel for us yeah oh of course
we got lots of names there I remember
the radio advertising we used to do yeah
they used to bring us large numbers of I
thought pretty good actually brought us
all kinds of crazy stuff but you know in
that I don't think there's anything
wrong with creating a narrow funnel I
mean it takes too much time and an
effort from you know your HR team to I
mean good lord you know when I was at
web methods we went through thousands of
resumes and you know you just you needed
the ability to really cut through all of
that paper reading and figure out you
know both in terms of you know
experience and skills as well as
personality and cultural fit like how
you know who we gonna pick up the phone
and call and who do we want to bring in
to interview I mean you need to create
that that narrow funnel so you know
saying all that to give you kudos
because it's in my mind it's a good
thing you want to cut out who you can
who needs to go as fast as you can yeah
I think that was the big problem within
this while we had a nice unfair
advantage against most of those DC
people they were bland and bureaucratic
to a fault right you read their ads and
no one could tell whether this was for
them or not
right so they send their resume and so
they ever got every Tom Dick and Harry
well we did the repulsor attractor thing
and as you said we got a more
concentrated flow and I think that's the
right way to do it yeah okay let's go on
to the next topic something we've talked
about over the years is leadership what
it means you know is it changing what
are the challenges you know what do you
see out there in the nature of
leadership and business land today well
as always I mean I think the topic of
leadership is is a fascinating one and I
think that especially in what I do
specifically because a lot of it is not
just you know I I work with leaders I do
a lot of individual coaching I also do a
lot of team level work
and I really have seen a big shift to
number one people who don't you know who
get into leadership positions in them
and they don't you know kind of stay
still they're evolving they're openly
evolving and they're very they're more
inclusive they are they're inclusive of
the not just their leadership teams but
the broader organizations around them
which i think is is fascinating and i
think it leads to you know i think i can
i think it can lead to some scary things
for leaders I mean some vulnerabilities
and kind of exposing things about
yourself that might not be you know
textbook but I do think it's very
different then you know kind of in the
you know maybe well 10 15 years ago I
think leadership has evolved that the
topic of leadership learning about
leadership learning to become a leader I
think that has all I think it's evolved
quite quite a bit so you say the net
result is leadership's on average better
today than it was 15 years ago in your
experience I don't know that I can say
that it's better or worse organizations
writ large or different right I mean
we're organizations really no matter I
mean in large part are evolving too and
I just feel like nothing stays in place
for very long anymore and that we've got
leaders that recognize that and you know
are creating capability within their
organizations to kind of harness that
power of of change and evolution and
they don't just expect it from you know
kind of the broader organization and
teams but they they understand good
leaders that I've that I have worked
with and I don't work with all good
leaders but that I have worked with
really understand how that there's an
evolutionary aspect to them even that
you know is associated with that so not
good not bad just different and and
changing not staying the same right
leadership isn't the same I think 15
years ago than it is today
because of the change the pace of change
that we see in organizations does that
make sense yeah and I think I like what
I'm hearing here you know as you know I
basically retired from the business
world 20 years ago which is hard to
believe but it is almost that's not
quite 2018 you're
ago and back then we had you know some
of that flexible leadership that you
talked about but particularly in larger
organizations it was not the rule there
was a lot of people who you know came up
a hierarchical structure and felt most
comfortable in a well-defined the
hierarchical structure with boxes on a
chart and all that sort of stuff and you
know we obviously didn't operate that
way but we had to be very very careful
in selecting out those people who we
thought had leadership capabilities in a
more dynamic environment sounds like
there's a lot more such people today I
definitely think so and you know there
are I mean there's a lot of research out
there about you know the benefit of
hierarchy so when you think about some
people I don't particularly care for it
use the church quote/unquote as an
example or the the police force as an
example of the military as why hierarchy
can be important and necessary
I think there's benefit from from less
structure and that and we see that you
know maybe not in those types of
organizations but we think we do see
that being a little bit more pervasive
you know that that you don't have that
org chart view or charge drive me
freaking crazy you don't have you know
not every organization thinks of itself
in terms of how you know and people
don't think of themselves in terms of
where they fall on an org chart it's a
lot more fluid and it's a lot more flat
right yep and some of that I think it's
good but I also think there's some risks
associated with it as you may recall we
always had an org chart but we didn't
worship it we move stuff around we
redefine things on the fly
etc but I do think it is useful for the
org chart to exist but just not for it
to be worshipped I have seen some
companies that try to go with completely
without the org chart and I think it's
still out on the evidence and whether
that's where that really works or not
there's a company called valve which
runs the steam game network for instance
which is or a radical non org chart
self-organizing place and last I saw
they were starting to run into some
organizational issues and I got to about
300 people where some amount of
organization they may be finding might
be necessary you know but back to your
other point it's hard to imagine that
somebody could operate
in the old 1975 command-and-control
structure and today's very rapidly
changing environment every business
almost is being reinvented every few
years you know the speed of change
brought on by technology by the
marketplace by globalism it's amazing
and if you're not prepared to adapt yep
much more rapidly than you were 1975
you're going to be dead how do you see
the speed of change as a stressor to to
management and organizations well let me
just say I also find it amazing how many
companies try to create this extranet
try they do create an external brand
that does not reflect really who they
are inside and I think that is I don't
think I know that is something that just
absolutely drives me crazy because
number one it's false advertising but
you know there's a lot of companies I
think you don't know how to act don't
know how to behave don't know how to
manage don't know how to lead don't know
how to operate outside of that tight
command and control traditional top up
bottom down type of structure and yet
there they are force at some level to
you know create a brand especially when
it become comes to talent attraction
right but they they create a brand and
maybe they're not even forced they just
do it because that's the evolution right
but it's not true to how they who they
really are and I see a good bit of that
and that creates organizational
challenges as well you know I mean I
think in terms of the pace of change
it's I think sometimes it can be
industry specific but there's you know
and it's and it's I think it's tightly
coupled with technology and how
pervasive technology is within your
organization I mean there I don't know
that there are many types of companies
and organizations anymore that don't use
technology right whether it's just for
internal email you know what have you
all the way to technology playing some
major role in our offering and whether
it's you know you you physically build
something but you've got a supply chain
and so you're using technology from that
perspective to you are a technology
company I think the use of technology
has always been in the past you know ten
plus years the major driver of change I
think the thing that I tried to foot
stop
for a long time especially with leaders
was you know really understanding
culture and change right um and at a
different level than they had before and
and starting to think about change from
you know you're not gonna send your
leaders just out to go get trained or
your managers on good change management
skills right it's you can't boil this
stuff down to a two day training seminar
or you know a matrix of steps that you
need to take in order to be able to
manage quote-unquote change within your
organization that's really a mindset
shift and that you know having that talk
about mindset and what that change you
know and working with people to really
go through that change where they can
accept change they know how to work in
it they they know how to manage in it
they know how to lead in it I think is
been a big inflection point within you
know organizations and and for
individuals as well you think they're
doing it better than they used to
managing change yeah um yeah I mean I
think that there's more organizations
that are better at it now than they were
in the past and I think there are more
and more organizations that are starting
to harness that power that you know that
that energy that evolution so that it's
it's kind of like the air they breathe
right it's not this thing that comes
around and like socks them upside the
head but they're learning how to really
an you know kind of embrace it more but
I think that's so I mean it's so
prevalent to the world we live in today
I mean you can't how you get away from
it exactly you know one would expect if
nothing else you know evolutionary
pruning would make people better it
changes that rate of change continues to
accelerate those companies that haven't
figured out how to manage and a highly
changing environment a lot of them are
gonna die right remember the example
back in the DC area we had a really big
home improvements chain called Hechinger
x' kind of like a home depot or
something like that and the covered
Maryland and Delaware and Pennsylvania
parts of Virginia and they were actually
very very mediocre but they were big
enough that the Home Depot's and the
loza's of the world decided not to go
after the DC area until the very end
but when they finally did you know they
folded in about 18 months you know they
just did not change in the face of this
coming huge threat they had to see
coming and they just folded it's hard to
imagine companies that have survived
over the last 20 years in any kind of
dynamic environment haven't got the
least a bit better at the change
management game yeah you know I think
the other interesting piece about you
know really looking organizations that
are looking at change as constant and
the pace of it that you know as it
speeds up is it I feel like a lot of
companies have gotten closer to and
better about understanding their
customers yeah I mean that's oh I've
always been keep you don't understand
your customer how can you be in business
all right yeah but and and even in I
mean you know clients that I've worked
with in the federal space you know I
mean it's a it's really interesting
without you know kind of going into too
much detail it's really interesting to
work with organizations that have never
had to think about customer because if
you think about you know I mean in the
in the government a lot of times they
just don't or they don't understand
they've never done it and so they don't
understand how what they do impacts you
know whether it be you know the American
people across the board or other people
within their in their organization and
just having that concept of everybody's
got a customer I think is really has
evolved and they're gonna you know I see
organizations getting better about and
closer to that that customer piece which
I love I love it
yeah it's certainly something I've
always believed and it's something I
counsel all my startup people that I
invest in or on their boards or whatever
you know go out and you know we're even
still just thinking about your idea go
to the biggest annual conference in the
industry you're trying to enter you
learn a tremendous amount face-to-face
with people there's only so much you can
learn from internet research if you
don't understand your customer and what
problem they're trying to solve you
really shouldn't be in business yep well
this kind of you know fast-moving
customer centric world clearly a key
factor is you're gonna need to have
employees who are highly engaged right
or committed and yet we talked earlier
about the fact that perhaps the the
newest
generation of employees don't want to be
all that committed they want to sort of
think of themselves kind of as free
agents talk to me a little bit about the
issues around employee engagement and
what companies are doing to get better
employee engagement in this world yeah
that's a good question I mean I think
employee engagement is one of the big
you know kind of HR ish you know topics
and hot buttons out there right now
because there's a whole world I mean
there are entire companies that just do
employee engagement and that's
everything from you know what's what's
our growth strategy to how do we deal
with our culture how do we make sure
that there's alignment within our
organization between you know what we do
is a company our overall strategy and
our people job fit and compensation I
mean employee engagement is just it's a
big term and it's a big effort you know
within within organizations these days
and so I think there's a lot that's
going on to you know help organizations
really focus on what does employee
engagement mean for us what is that you
know what is our overall strategy what
makes sense given you know the business
we're in the the the type of workforce
that were you know that we're creating
etc but from my perspective I really
think about employee engagement when I'm
working with clients you know
essentially to think about you know kind
of belonging growth and alignment right
I mean how how do you create you know
that connection with your employees that
sense of pride and belonging so that
they feel that this is an organization
that they want to be you know a part of
and of course that reflects in how they
work with customers it's how they work
with their colleagues internally from a
growth standpoint you know how our
organizations committing to their
employees how are they supporting their
development how are they supplying
growth opportunities and you know kind
of how planning for that on a bigger
scale than they have in the past and
then and lastly alignment you know do we
do we understand
and you know what employees are looking
for and can we line up our expectations
both in terms of the organization you
know leadership managers and our
employees so that we are we're growing
the commitment that we want them to have
you know both to our customers as well
as to you know kind of the strategic
goals of the of the organization and so
you know I think when you think about
all of those pieces and and you know
there's different models you know out
there in terms of you know what
encompasses an overall employee
engagement strategy but I really again
you know I really think about kind of
that belonging that growth in the
alignment and how that kind of creates
an engagement and gets all the the major
you know pillars the you know people
organization leadership involved and
driving that engagement and so you know
I really think organizations are paying
a lot more attention to it you know I
feel like there was a period in time
maybe and and we still do it at some
level but there was a big focus on
feedback right like getting feedback
from our employees what do they like
what are they not like you know let's
keep it simple let's you know blow it
out and start doing focus groups what do
we do with all of this data oh my god
we've got employees you know that are
unhappy and then there's you know then
you you kind of get you know HR and
sometimes leadership into a position
where they're running around frantically
trying to correct things from this new
data that they've that they've collected
and that I think can have its own
negative consequence because surveys and
trying to respond to them can be I think
really dangerous if not done well so I
think having an employee engagement
strategy is really kind of getting
people to shift mentally about how they
think about how we get information and
share it and how we put new strategies
in place to you know kind of create a
holistic approach to keep this
organizational machine moving but on the
flip side of that you know these younger
generations I mean the gig economy right
we are the gig economy and there's a lot
of people that don't want to go to work
for organizations they want to do the
work but they don't want to be a part of
your organization and so they're
figuring out ways that they can stand on
the periphery and just kind of 1099
their weigh-in and I don't know that I
can speak to how I have in my mind ideas
about how that's really gonna what role
that's gonna play in organizations you
know down the road I've seen a lot of
companies who are getting rid of their
infrastructure right I mean how great to
not have to have that office building
what a tremendous cost but then that
comes with its own set of challenges
so I kind of dipped into a couple of
different topics there but I think I
answered the question overall yeah the
engagement areas an area I'm quite
interested in in fact I put a little
plug in for one of my investment
companies called voter vo HTR dot-com
you know they've got a very cool product
for what I would call continuous
lightweight surveying they do a survey
question every day often it's just a fun
question would you rather be rich or
famous that kind of thing but they
recommend that their clients put about
one-third of the questions to be you
know business-related and actionable and
the results of that thing are to my mind
much better than those tedious once a
year 60 question questionnaires that are
administered by some consulting firm
takes four or five months with a
consulting firm they analyze the results
and finally present it to management
probably too late and then nothing ever
happens yep I'm a much bigger than real
time measurement but of course you have
to have a management team that's
committed to listening and actually
doing something with it yeah absolutely
and I will tell you I I had a client
once who wanted to do a survey every
year and mainly because he really wanted
to win an award that was given out to
companies in the DC area every year and
I was coached they brought me on
obviously as a consultant and I was
coached by his leadership team that I
had to take him downstairs to a
restaurant and feed him a couple of
martinis before I gave him the results
so that you know not just listening but
being okay with the fact if things
aren't great absolutely and in fact when
we've been selling the voter product we
have found a surprising number of
bunnies that really are not
intellectually honest they really don't
want to hear the truth
absolutely that's pretty sick if you ask
me as you'll recall our number one value
in all rut companies is intellectual
honesty you know let the chips fall
where they may but perhaps even maybe
more than back in the day it seems like
there are people that want to live in
cloud cuckoo-land and don't want the
truth what's that all about well and I
think the other thing that you you know
that you really impressed upon me was
being able to speak your mind right and
I remember and I've got it somewhere a
very crisp statement from you that said
and if you feel like you can't don't
work here anymore
this is not a punitive organization
where if you say something you know if
you think something say it basically but
you know there's a lot of organizations
out there that don't have that kind of
culture and you will you you there could
be punitive action taken if you you know
and I'm not talking about I'm talking
like at the intellectual level right not
like what do you think of this guy over
here I mean hey we're working on this
projects it's going sideways what do you
what do you think we need to do right no
you got a you got a toe the line it's
incredible to me how many organizations
I have met that number one do that you
know and and don't try to to squelch
that that piece of it and then don't
want to hear the truth or flat-out will
say I don't really think that that's the
way that things are and we're not gonna
do anything about it seems like it's a
lot more of that going on I think one of
the classic examples I don't you
remember this was a an engineer at
Google who wrote a long thoughtful and
controversial piece on why Google was
having problems hiring women as
engineers yep I think his name was James
day more and yeah as far as I could tell
he was attempting to be intellectually
honest you know he violated some civil
lists of HR politeness but he hasn't
getting fired for that for floating a
document on an internal discussion board
that was meant for the purposes of
discussion of ideas including you know
fringe ideas and this thing violated
some level of political correctness
sufficiently badly that they fired him
now what kind of signal does that send
to your organization it sends that you
need to shut the fuck up signal exactly
and of course part of that is being
driven by you know today's HR
departments I must tell you when I talk
to friends who are still working in big
corporate America they all go on
endlessly about how much HR sucks I mean
what we used to think that it wasn't
done well it was kind of a waste of time
but now I hear a lot more about it being
a positive evil yeah any any of any of
that in your experience well you know
it's funny I mean even though I started
off my career in HR from the consulting
perspective I have never gone in to a
client effort working with human
resources they might become a part of
the process once I'm in but I somehow
kind of became an antichrist of HR in a
lot of ways and I think that in and of
itself kind of says quite a bit about HR
like you don't need any improvement
especially giving the work I do right
leadership developments culture change
you know you would think that HR would
be my caveat into the work that I do but
but it very rarely is that said I mean I
feel like there is just I don't know I
mean maybe there will always just be
some aspect of HR that is a necessary
evil quote unquote like you said in
terms of they you know do recruiting
they do employee paperwork they do you
know but I still don't feel that
across-the-board HR has done enough to
really try to understand and evolve in a
way that's like hey people are the most
important part of an organization like
that's clearly in your wheelhouse can
you do something more revolutionary than
what you're doing now and it and it
feels like again clients that I work
with they just want to work around HR
because HR has never given them anything
to really
you know drive any part of the business
drive any part of shopping that's
probably not fair across the board but
they I don't know just it just feels
stuffy and it feels old-school yeah
that's the kind of complaints that I'm
hearing from people out in the field and
I remember we know we built our
organization our HR organization at
Thompson so that it was central to our
strategy you know I people ask me how I
spent my time I said I spent a third of
my time on making sure our HR
organization was the best that we could
possibly have out there and you know you
may recall we divided it up into three
parts basically recruiting retention and
development and then the third part for
the transactional management of
insurance programs that kind of stuff
and I thought that was that produced a
pretty damn good result for us and you
know some of our alums have taken those
ideas with them and I think it worked
out well for them but what you're seeing
what my friends are seeing is that in
general at best HR is a nuisance and at
worst it can be a big obstacle yeah well
you know you were talking about the the
guy from Google right well you know did
you I don't know I mean I'm sure you did
it some level paid attention to you know
kind of everything that happened at uber
right and as I was reading along as
different things unfolded at uber what
amazed me was the role that I mean HR
was culpable in that situation right of
you know women filing complaints about
things that were happening in the
workplace and you know soft-pedaling I
mean just not jumping in and doing their
job and I was really blown away and I
was even more blown away when they fired
the CEO and I'm like you need to walk
the head of HR out because that person
did a grave injustice to the
organization and to the employees that
were saying hey we've got some sexual
harassment issues here I was really
surprised and I really felt like that
was an opportunity to kind of shake up
HR the concept of HR the role of HR but
I also feel like they're so in the
pockets of other executives in the
company that in a lot of organizations
they're probably toeing the line right
instead of really able to say hey this
not okay this is not what we're doing we
are not gonna soft-pedal this we're not
gonna bury this we're gonna deal with it
immediately so they kind of get a bad
rap from all angles I mean and yeah
there are those organizations out there
that are much more I think futuristic
but I feel like they've got some
coverage up above them that gives them
the freedom and the flexibility to be to
be different right and not all leaders
want to deal with HR problems
yeah well this goes back to you know my
prime directive intellectual honesty at
all levels at all times and it's still
amazing why would you want anything else
but the truth because if you're trying
to make decisions you're always in
business trying to make decisions on
limited information and if the
information you have isn't the best
available and isn't the truth so the
best your people and your organization
knows it you inevitably will make worse
decisions so it strikes me that this
uber kind of cover-up is yet another
example of people failing to live to the
code of intellectual honesty yeah and I
and I think it's just you know also at
some level just good common sense you
know I mean if you've got an individual
let alone a number of individuals who've
come forward to say we've we've got a
problem because this person over here
you know has has done something to me I
mean you've got responsibility number
one to to take action right I mean it's
not necessarily in that moment make a
decision but it's there's some type of
action that needs to come from that to
get to the truth about you know what's
happening but you know where's your
where's your moral compass and you know
in all of this I mean you don't let
things like that just fester and and go
away or get to the point where now
you've got you know people who are
leaving their jobs because you're not
doing your job and taking care of that
situation you know at some level so I
would hope that it's a in large part you
know speaks to the type of people and
the type of leadership that's within the
company right and like I said I mean
they walk the CEO out they should have
walked the head of HR on at the same
time
my mind yep absolutely let's move on to
another topic that's you know related
the things we were just talking about
which is one of the things I think is
actually been a good movement in general
in our workplaces but there's been some
issues and there's some ways to go which
is the issues around women and men in
the workplace right yeah one of my
favorites yeah a lot more women in
senior positions though not yet pro rata
so if you look up the pipeline a little
ways it's quite interesting to see that
the percentages of men and women in the
elite MBA programs in law school medical
school almost exactly 50/50 in four-year
colleges it's more like 58 59 % women so
the pipeline should be driving a
continued closing of these gaps but they
still exist love to hear your thoughts
on I'm not sure what the right word is
gender dynamics in the workforce I guess
I mean a lot has happened there for
instance since you know since we worked
together and you know one of the things
that is really that has really stuck
with me is that what we want to see and
we still as you mentioned have a ways to
go I mean just across the board and
women in leadership positions women in
leadership positions in Fortune 500
companies women on boards you know just
the presence of women in organizations I
think some aspect of dare I say you know
kind of now we've got the me2 movement
right so that has put a whole other I
think layer of complexity around men and
women in the in the workplace and have a
good friend who you know we enjoy the
fact that we don't see eye to eye on
everything because we can really rudl
around topics and we were kind of
talking about lean in and she's like no
man we got to lean out and we've got you
know everybody just needs to women need
to do what they've got to do and we've
got to encourage men to want to have
better relationships with women in the
workplace as women want to have better
relationships with men and so I have not
and I mentioned this to you I've not
been in a position where I've seen
personally the relationships I've had
with men in the workplace have all been
really great ones whether you know it be
the men that I work
with or the men that have worked you
know for me over time you know
long-standing relationships like similar
to ours where I'm in the company of
equals and I'm always in learning mode
and I'm always looking for people that I
can learn from but I don't know I think
that there's probably a tension that's
growing I work with some organizations
that are women-owned businesses and
they're pretty proudly all women some of
them and that kind of gives me a little
bit of pause like wow if you're only
focused on you know it should be the
right person for the job not and they're
not necessarily just not focused on
hiring men it's just kind of how their
evolution their growth evolution has
gone what are we gonna do you know are
we gonna be are we gonna see more
organizations that are all men or women
and are we gonna stop learning how to
you know kind of how to work together I
don't know I mean honestly I don't know
where this is going I just think it's
there's a lot happening that's really
fascinating and that needs to drive a
bigger conversation certainly within
leadership teams within organizations
yep
and yeah I'm hearing all kinds of weird
things about that you know that here we
are seeing very qualified women come to
the workplace we see women moving into
executive ranks but now it's kind of a
backlash around this me too thing you
know you hear men say no I'm a I'm not
gonna hire any women I'm just opening
myself up for a potential problem down
the road even if I pure as the driven
snow and that's certainly not the result
we want and you know this idea of a
woman only company I mean to my mind
that's every bit as bad as a men only
company yeah yeah let's hope we can get
past these challenges I mean overall I
mean I got to tell you the me2 thing is
real I mean I know number of women have
horrifying stories from the workplace
and I've known some perpetrators on the
male side in fact you probably don't
even know this at tier we had one who
sexually harassed one of the women in
the most gross and crude possible
fashion and you know being kind of
old-school rather than dealing with HR I
called him up I said when Dad was office
it said if you ever tried such a thing
again I'd break both of his fucking legs
right two weeks later he resigned
now that was probably not a little
impolitic li incorrect but it worked but
you know those foul people are been out
there but we can't let the you know a
tiny percentage of foul people ruin
gender equality in the workplace and you
know there's some signs that it might
yeah and and you can't let it ruin the
power that comes from you know just
hiring great people whether they're men
or women and and and creating you know
teams that have different perspectives
and have different experiences and and
can create really amazing outcomes
within organizations right you don't
want to pass that up either and I and I
know I mean I I definitely you know
there's there's definitely been an
impact you know in in my life it's just
you know it hasn't been so grotesque
that I haven't been able to you know
kind of fight back and at some level get
kind of get closure around things but I
also you know I I think everybody needs
to be more mindful of our behavior right
then like let's hearken back to your
interview style at Thompson right where
you always made a point to say fuck in
an interview so that people understood
kind of what they were getting
themselves into well you think that that
would be okay in this day and age would
you still do that it was it my company I
sure shit what right if I work for a big
corporation my guess is they they
wouldn't like it like I have to tell you
a funny story here's what my favorite HR
stories when I the first day I went to
work at network solutions as the new CEO
brought by top thirty people together
which here's an interesting bad sign
those top thirty people never even
brought together before which by itself
was a sign of how screwed up that place
was I gave him a 45-minute pep talk and
you know vision of what I had in mind
for the company and you know what needed
to be fixed and where we were going but
what tremendous opportunity we all had
together here and I used the word fuck
three times quite humorously
the next day I get a call from the head
of
the organization included HR at our
parent SAIC which was a big Beltway
bandit and at the time I came took the
job they were actually the majority
shareholder but one of my terms and
conditions for taking the job was that
they would within two weeks sell down
their stock to less than 50 percent but
anyway during that interim two-week
period in theory I reported to them and
so I get the call from the hates are
ahead of you one level above HR I got
this report day you said fuck three
times was that true I go fuck yeah and
then I that you'll love this an HR
person we will not name so we don't
embarrass her
I had a directly researched the use of
the word fuck in a non-sexual sense as
an intensifier back at Thompson it's
written it's nice four or five paragraph
analysis that said it's absolutely not
sexual harassment the safe fuck as long
as this an intensifier and not referring
to a sexual act was brilliantly written
with the complete straight face but
fortunately I had it on my email I
pulled it up and I read that back to
this guy and he said oh yeah I guess
you're actually right about that but I
really really wish you wouldn't say fuck
that I said fuck that hung up I love it
well I'll tell you a similar story
rather um Jon Gleason remember him yeah
our IT guy we had a lot of ideas well I
mean he was like our like fixed our
computers up in octo okay Oh Jason John
Eason
he's an ISA nice and you're right John
Eason my bad I'll never bring out John
easily right so I have after I left
Thompson and did my ever so brief stint
with you at network solutions
it was my ID maybe Ben at web methods
for about a week and you know we had I
mean we were a start-up right so we were
in a space that we were subletting from
a sublet from a sublet and it was like
boxes and used furniture and anyway
Giessen came over because he was
dropping off a cd-rom that he burned off
my computer of my old emails from
Thompson and instead of writing like you
know Sarah's emails or whatever he wrote
porno files and left it on the front
desk and said this is for Sara Ken
spotter and left and I mean I was in HR
and I got in trouble at fern HHR and I
was like basically I was like me and two
other people and I thought that was
really funny I'm like you know we got a
light at lighten up it at some level
it's clearly a joke you know but it was
a it created a little bit of a tiff in
my new HR capacity yeah I don't like
that I mean you know I still think you
should be able to say fuck as an
intensifier right why the hell not you
know for the reasons this HR
professional laid out in exquisite
detail I don't know what the argument
would be against it other than general
squeamishness ya know and I and I
totally agree with you and I also don't
admittedly tend to be squeamish and I
use it as a general intensifier pretty
often and I also think that you know
when I look back on my career and the
teams that I've worked on you know there
was you know a very work hard play hard
mentality that has always been you know
something that career-wise has followed
me I'm a play hard kind of person and so
I think about you know times when we
would go out to happy hour or our
Christmas parties or what-have-you I
mean that really helped build a sense of
team you know having the opportunity to
know your co-workers your colleagues in
a different setting and to be able to
you know learn more about them burn off
some steam you know have some cocktails
whatever I mean I really feel like that
is essential to becoming a team right we
are not like one-dimensional people we
you and I have talked about this at the
Lincoln Financial Leadership Summit
right where you don't come to work as
one person and then you go home and
you're a totally different person and so
you know when we get into these levels
of sensitivity where people just kind of
they you know they engage but they do it
in a very vanilla fashion and they don't
engage outside of you know whatever the
very specific work thing is like what
does that do you know to our sense of
of Temar sense of camaraderie our
ability to you know kind of get things
done at a you know kind of firing on all
cylinders level yep and that's I think
one of the things it's give that's
really given up if you allow the HR
police to you no sensor all kinds of
good-hearted you know honest
interactions because they violate some
you know shibboleths of you know the HR
ordinances and I know damn well that
you're not supposed to say fuck in
corporate America anymore but I think
that's stupid I think that's a bad idea
and just the kind of there's no purpose
there's no sexual harassment involved
and saying fuck as an intensifier
it's just they you know run amok sense
of you know school our machinist or
something yeah well and it's you know
it's it's cya and that's pervasive right
how are we gonna cover our ass and just
you know strip out all of the things
that might make individuals individuals
but then won't offend or upset others
shit if people get offended fuck them
right in fact my views the word offended
is the first sign of a bullshitter yeah
you know it's a lot of my last five
years studying neuro cognitive science
and cognitive science itself and one of
the areas I've studied is emotion well
guess what there is no emotion called
offended
it's a pseudo emotion people use them
alit manipulate other people so whenever
you hear someone say I'm offended and I
want to just put in square brackets I'm
a phony bullshit or trying to
psychologically manipulate you it'll
provide a lot of insight that what's
really going on well but you know the
word offended like it strikes a chord
with me like it strikes an emotion that
is you know is real like when I hear
somebody say well that offends me I'm
like oh my god like I I mean it it makes
me react in a certain way in what way
good bad or indifferent it makes me I
don't think it's good or bad it makes me
want to back away from that individual
exactly I mean I'll go farther makes me
think they're a bullshitter and a
manipulator yeah I think people fly that
flag too fast and too often sometimes
but anyway I use a different word it
makes me angry I feeling
salted by it right I feel humiliated and
diminished right you know say something
that's real fuck you that's what I have
to say about in on right yeah this hyper
/ sensitivity you know I was just that
ain't the way to do it least in my
opinion I'm an old fogy I'm retired but
hey that's that's what you get for the
advice you get for paying exactly what
you paid to listen to the gym ruts show
podcast which is nothing yeah well but
you know what else gem I mean think
about it like if you've got people
around you that are offended what do you
do you put distance between and then
this is a part of like a growing
systemic problem right like okay I'm not
gonna hang out with that person because
they're offended they're too easily
offended you know they they use that
term you know too often and so then you
feel like oh god I mean what do i do how
do I talk to them how you know then you
end up trying to twist yourself into a
pretzel or you don't and you're like I
just I'm not gonna hang out with that
person I'm gonna be around them anymore
I mean it's like one of those social
stipulations I feel like that just makes
us more more divisive anyway we've
probably beat that horse yep and I think
we're kind of coming up on our time here
so I think we'll wrap her up I want to
thank you Sarah for a very interesting
confirm a little wild conversation that
we've had here today well thank you for
having me I am as I looked at your other
interviews and I've and I've listened to
them and they've they've all been
fantastic I wasn't exactly how I was
gonna pitch and hold myself in on this
on the gym rat show but it's it's been
great I mean we always find ourselves in
a situation where we cover a broad
number of topics certainly with
different opinions and I'm really
grateful thing I think it's been great
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]